xz926813@ohio.edu, Columbus, OH, USA

Xianlong Zeng

Updated 08/2021



Research Interest

My research interests lie in Big Data Analysis and Artificial Intelligence, particularly building big data processing interfaces and tailored deep learning architectures for real-world problem-solving. I am also passionate about applying modern machine learning techniques to domains such as Healthcare and Education Learning.

Education

Ohio University (OU), Ohio	Aug. 2016 Dec 2021 (expected)
Ph.D. in Electrical and Computer Engineering	GPA: 4.0/4
Ohio University (OU), Ohio	Aug. 2014 Apr. 2016
M.S. in Mathematics	GPA: 3.3/4
University of Science and Technology Beijing (USTB), Beijing	Sep. 2010 Jun. 2014
B.S. in Mathematics	GPA: 3.4/4
Fu Jen Catholic University (FJU), Taiwan	Jan. 2013 Jul. 2013
Student Exchange Program, Mathematics	

Publications

Journal Article

- Xianlong Zeng, Simon Lin, Chang Liu. "Multi-View Deep Learning Framework for Predicting Patient Expenditure in Healthcare." *IEEE OJCS*. 2021.
- Peng, Jin(*), Xianlong Zeng(*), Janice Townsend, Gilbert Liu, Yungui Huang, and Simon Lin. "A Machine Learning Approach to Uncovering Hidden Utilization Patterns of Early Childhood Dental Care Among Medicaid-Insured Children." Frontiers in Public Health, 2021.
- En-Ju Lin, Jennifer Hefner, **Xianlong Zeng**, Soheil Moosavinasab, Thomas Huber, Jennifer Klima, Chang Liu, and Simon Lin. "A deep learning model for pediatric patient risk stratification." *American Journal of Managed Care*, 2019.

Conference

- Xianlong Zeng, Fanghao Song, Zhongen Li, Krerkkiat Chusap, and Chang Liu. "Human-in-the-loop model explanation via verbatim boundary identification in generated neighborhoods." *International Cross-Domain Conference, CD-MAKE 2021*, Digital Conference, Aug. 2021.
- Xianlong Zeng, Simon Lin, and Chang Liu. "Transformer-based unsupervised patient representation learning based on medical claims for risk stratification and analysis." *ACM BCB*, Digital Conference, Aug. 2021.
- Xianlong Zeng, Simon Lin, Chang Liu. "Multilevel Self-attention Model and Its Use on Medical Risk Prediction." *PACIFIC SYMPOSIUM ON BIOCOMPUTING*, Hawaii, USA, 2019.

Preprint

- Xianlong Zeng, Simon Lin, and Chang Liu. "Pre-training Transformer-based Framework on Large-scale Pediatric Claims Data for Downstream Population-specific Tasks." *arXiv preprint (under review by Scientific Reports)*, 2021.
- Xianlong Zeng, Soheil Moosavinasab, En-Ju D Lin, Simon Lin, Razvan Bunescu, Chang Liu. "Distributed representation of patients and its use for medical cost prediction." *arXiv preprint*, 2021.

Conference Poster

• **Zeng, Xianlong,** Soheil Moosavinasab, Enju Lin, Yungui Huang, Chang Liu, and Simon Lin. "DeepChild: Hospitalization Prediction via Neural Network." *AMIA*, *San Francisco*, *USA*, 2021.

Honors & Awards

Winner of the Three Minute Thesis (3MT) Competition	2021
Winner in the DII National Data Science Challenge	2019
Russ College Graduate Scholarships for Ph.D Degree	2016-2021
Mathematics Graduate Scholarships for Master Degree	2014-2016

Talks

Human-in-the-loop model explanation via verbatim boundary identification in generated neighborhoods	2021
Host & Location: CD-MAKE, virtual event	
Transformer-based unsupervised patient representation learning	2021
Host & Location: ACM-BCB, virtual event	
A Deep Learning Model for Pediatric Patient Risk Stratification	2019
Host & Location: OSU CCTS, OSU center.	
Sepsis Mortality Prediction using Deep Learning	2019
Host & Location: UT Health School of Biomedical Informatics, Houston, USA	

Research Experience

Ohio University & Nationwide Children's Hospital

Research topic: Medical Risk Stratification using Deep Learning

Jun. 2017 -- Present

Principal Investigator: Dr. Simon Lin and Dr. Chang Liu

- Developed pre-processing algorithms based on *Python* and *Jupyter* for processing large-scale medical transactions, and reduce computation time by 80%.
- Designed algorithms (i.e., *MSAM* and *Multi-view*), for high-risk patient identification and future medical cost prediction. Three related papers are published.
- Designed algorithms for patient representation learning, which enables similar patient extraction and patient subtyping. One related paper is published.
- Designed algorithms for medical code embedding learning and cross-generation medical code mapping, and improve the performance of downstream applications by more than 50%. Two related papers are published

Ohio University

Research topic: Explainable artificial intelligence (XAI)

Aug. 2019 -- Aug. 2020

Principal Investigator: Dr. Chang Liu

• Developed visualization tools and black-box explaining tools for model interpretation, particularly focusing on deep learning models on image dataset, such as *MINST*. One related paper is published, and Two papers are under review.

Research topic: Software Bug Report Localization

Aug. 2017 -- Aug. 2018

Principal Investigator: Dr. Chang Liu

- Developed a pipeline to crawl, process, and store the bug reports from open-source software on *GitHub*, and more than 40000 reports are collected.
- Designed algorithms for software bug report localization and identification, and improve accuracy by 15%.

Research topic: Food image recognition and calorie estimation

Aug. 2016 -- Aug. 2017

Principal Investigator: Dr. Chang Liu

- Developed a pipeline to crawl, process, and store the food images from websites.
- Designed algorithms for food image recognition and segmentation on smart phone, and reduce computation time by 10% and improve accuracy by 5%. More than 40000 reports are collected.

Teaching Experience

Ohio University Computer Science Department

Aug. 2016 – Apr. 2021

- Design and Analysis of Algorithms (Teaching Assistant)
- Introduction to Computer Science in C++ (Teaching Assistant)
- Game Design (Teaching Assistant)
- Computational Theory (Teaching Assistant)

Ohio University Mathematics Department

Aug. 2014 -- Apr 2016

- College Algebra (Lecturer)
- Calculus I (Lecturer)

Work Experience

Research IT R&D at Nationwide Children's Hospital. Data Scientist Intern.

Project topic: Apply Word2vec and Doc2vec to Medical Domain

Jun. 2017 -- Sep. 2017

- Wrote the design document of tailored medical-word2vec algorithm in Python and finished the implementation, which successfully compiled using the large-scale medical claims data and achieved 80% reduction in training time.
- Wrote the design document of tailored medical-doc2vec algorithm in Python and finished the implementation, which outperformed local commercial model by more than 60% in accuracy and impact an additional \$5 millions in cost.

Project topic: Predict High-cost Patient using Language Models

Jun. 2018 -- Sep. 2019

- Wrote the design document of PMCA algorithm in Python, and finished the implementation, which is the key baseline in many related research projects.
- Wrote the design document of tailored LSTM, CNN, and Transformer algorithms in Python and finished the implementation, and reduced the high-utilizer identification error rate by 30%.
- Built a UI where a user can write query, and the query results are visualized on the map with selected coloring gradient and resolution, which involves writing HTML, JavaScript, and Jupiter.
- Built interpretability toolbox for predictive deep learning models to help physicians understand the results. These tools help to bridge the gaps between medical physicians and AI researchers.

Skills

Operating System: Mac OS X, Linux, Windows.

Language: Python, C, C++, Java, SQL, Golang, Javascript, ReactJS, PHP, HTML, CSS.

Tools: Git, Matlab, Spark, JUnit, Flask, Amazon EC2, RESTful, ElasticSearch, Google Cloud, Unity.

References

Liu Chang, Professor, Ohio University

- Email: liuc@ohio.edu
- Homepage: https://www.ohio.edu/engineering/about/people/liuc

Simon Lin, Chief Research Information Officer, Nationwide Children's Hospital

- Email: Simon.Lin@nationwidechildrens.org
- Homepage: https://www.nationwidechildrens.org/find-a-doctor/profiles/simon-m-lin